Ian Channing

Lead AI Engineer

20 years of software engineering experience across AI, engineering, statistical visualisation, and market risk. Builder of stable, robust systems—often solo—from research prototypes to high-value products. I now research and test the limits of LLMs

Contact Information

Location: Lier, Belgium
Phone: +32 491 482 747
Email: ian@ianchanning.com
Website: ianchanning.com
Languages: English, Dutch

About

I have 20 years software engineering experience across AI, engineering and statistical visualization startups and market risk (investment banking). I moved from London to Belgium and speak fluent Dutch. I architected and scaled, almost single-handedly, a data visualization platform that grew with a 3 person university research project to a \$50m buyout in 8 years. I like to tackle hard problems, whilst the code I write and the data I model has a history of being stable and robust. I now work extensively with LLMs, researching their capabilities, building data pipelines, models and applications where necessary.

Work Experience

Charp (Oct 2023 – Present)

Lead AI Engineer

Charp is a KU Leuven spin off, an IoT platform that monitors the environment for some of the most famous art works in Belgium and Europe. Building and stabilising the time-series data pipelines. Building extremely robust python IoT Bluetooth gateways for data capture. Building AI models using the data pipeline, expert level LLM context management, deploying agents and context engineering. Skills: Python · TypeScript · Postgres · InfluxDB · Google Cloud · LLMs

MONA.health (Feb 2022 – Sep 2023)

AI Engineer

Mona is a spin off from KU Leuven, with the head of the KU Leuven glaucoma research as a founder. Data platform for ophthalmologists and endocrinologists to handle scanned retinal images and generate AI predictions for diabetic retinopathy and glaucoma. Training AI vision model as well as building out the Flask API and integrating it with the TypeScript application.

Skills: Python TypeScript Node.js GraphQL Postgres Docker Terraform AWS

imec $(Jul\ 2018 - Jan\ 2022)$

Software Architect, Lead Data Engineer

Building an in house polyglot data framework to handle all the various data sources within imec. Used for experience sampling and large scale user research throughout Belgium. Optimising python code for building AI models for smart cities. Internal training and talks for AI.

Skills: JavaScript Node.js GraphQL Postgres Python

Permasense (August 2009 – Jun 2018)

Lead Data Visualisation Engineer (via Konsulting then Blank Slate)

Working for an Imperial spin off, Permasense, that became the worldwide number one provider of ultrasonic corrosion monitoring systems to the oil and gas industry. I architected and scaled, almost single-handedly, a data visualisation platform that grew as part of a 3 person university research project to a \$50m buyout to Emerson in 8 years. It is a robust, performant data visualization platform - almost

bug free in production for 6 years.

Skills: JavaScript Python React SQL Server REST

(Sep 2010 - Jan 2017) Konsulting

Data Visualisation Engineer

Contracting for Permasense (see above) as well as contracting out to my previous company VSN.

VSN International (Apr 2007 – Jan 2017)

Data Visualisation Engineer £3M government funded large-scale distributed data visualization research project with Leeds University and the Numerical Algorithms Group. React application for generating design of experiments for statisticians.

Skills: React Java C MySQL Distributed Computing

(Jul 2001 - Mar 2007) Credit Suisse

Analyst Developer (Market Risk IT)

Working on three separate successful strategic projects. A department wide data platform, a C# ad hoc Market Risk query tool and a SQL Server data warehouse.

Skills: C# SQL Server Data Warehousing Excel VBA

Education

(Oct 1997 – Jun 2001) Imperial College London

MSci, Mathematics and Computer Science

Upper second ~ 3.5 GPA

Dissertation: Macroeconomic forecasting

Birkbeck College, London (Oct 2004 – Jun 2007)

MSc, Economics

Merit ~ 3.7 GPA

Dissertation: Regional Life Expectancy in England

Stanford University, Coursera

Machine Learning, Certificate

96%

Linear / Logistic Regression, Neural Networks, SVMs, Cluster Analysis

(Sep 2017 - Mar 2018)Coursera

Deep Learning (5-course specialisation), Certificate

Neural Networks, Hyperparameter tuning, Regularization, CNNs, Residual Networks, Python, Tensor-

Awards / Achievements

Credit Suisse Annual Award

(Jul 2007)

Part of inaugural winning team in London to Paris Enduroman (relay run to Dover, channel swim and cycle to Paris) challenge alongside charity fund raising in excess of £150,000.

Lands End to John O'Groats cycle challenge - 1400km in 7 days

(Jul 2008)

Cycled with a friend the length of the British Isles in one week to help him win a bet for charity.

References

Available on request.

(Sep 2015 - Nov 2015)